Mushroom Bourguignon By Melissa Clark (NYT)

YIELD: 4 to 6 servings

INGREDIENTS

6 tablespoons butter or extra-virgin olive oil, plus more as needed

2 pounds mixed mushrooms, such as portobello, cremini, white button, shiitake or oyster, cut into 1-inch chunks (about 10 cups)

8 ounces peeled pearl onions (2 cups), larger ones cut in half

Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper

1 large leek or 2 small leeks, white and light green parts, diced (1 1/2 cups)

2 carrots, thinly sliced

3 garlic cloves (2 minced, 1 grated to a paste)

1 tablespoon tomato paste

2 ½ tablespoons all-purpose flour

1 ½ cups dry red wine

1 ½ cups beef, mushroom or vegetable broth

1 tablespoon tamari or soy sauce, plus more to taste

3 large fresh thyme branches or 1/2 teaspoon dried thyme

1 bay leaf

3 to 4 ounces chanterelle or oyster mushrooms, thinly sliced (about 1 cup)

Smoked paprika, for serving

Polenta, egg noodles or mashed potatoes, for serving

Chopped flat-leaf parsley, for serving

PREPARATION

Add 2 tablespoons butter or oil to a large Dutch oven or pot and set it over medium heat. When the fat is hot, stir in half the mushrooms and half the pearl onions. (If it doesn’t all fit in the pot in one layer, you might have to do this in three batches, rather than two.) Without moving them around too much, cook the mushrooms until they are brown on one side, about 3 minutes. Stir and let them brown on the other side, 2 to 3 minutes more. Use a slotted spoon to transfer mushrooms and onions to a large bowl or plate and sprinkle with salt and pepper. Repeat with another 2 tablespoons butter and the remaining mushrooms and pearl onions, seasoning them as you go.

Reduce heat to medium-low. Add another 1 tablespoon butter or oil to pan. Add leeks and carrot and sauté until the leeks turn lightly golden and start to soften, 5 minutes. Add the 2 minced garlic cloves and sauté for 1 minute longer.

Stir in tomato paste and cook for 1 minute. Stir in flour and cook, stirring, for 1 minute, then add wine, broth, 1 tablespoon tamari, thyme and bay leaf, scraping up the brown bits at bottom of pot.

Add reserved cooked mushrooms and pearl onions back to the pot and bring to a simmer. Partly cover the pot and simmer on low heat until carrots and onions are tender and sauce is thick, 30 to 40 minutes. Taste and add more salt and tamari if needed. Stir in the grated garlic clove.

Just before serving, heat a small skillet over high heat and add 1/2 tablespoon butter or oil. Add half of the sliced chanterelles or oyster mushrooms and let cook without moving until they are crisp and brown on one side, 1 to 2 minutes. Flip and cook on the other side. Transfer to a plate and sprinkle with salt and smoked paprika. Repeat with remaining butter and mushrooms. Serve mushroom Bourguignon over polenta, noodles or mashed potatoes, topped with fried mushrooms and parsley.

David Malosh for The New York Times

Meaty mushrooms simmered with pearl onions, wine and carrots make for a rich, wintry Bourguignon-style stew. The quality of the stock here makes a big difference, so if you’re not using homemade, buy a good brand. If you’re a meat eater, beef broth adds a familiar brawny character to this dish, but mushroom or vegetable broth work just well, especially because the whole dish is rounded out with a tamari for depth. For the best flavor, use as many kinds of mushrooms as you can get, and let them really brown when searing; that caramelization adds a lot of depth to the sauce. Maitake mushrooms give this a brisketlike texture, in a very good way.

Dried mushrooms work well. One ounce will replace 8 ounces of fresh. Reconstitute by soaking in boiling water for 30 minutes. Lift the mushroom pieces out of the liquid and cut as needed. Let the liquid stand for a few minutes to let any grit settle, then pour off the clear liquid and use it as part of the broth in the recipe. Discard the murky remains.

Many varieties of dried mushrooms are available in supermarkets and stores like Trader Joe's, Aldi and Sprouts & online through Amazon.

Tasting helps, but in general “dry” red wines are those that are not considered fruity. In an article about using wine for cooking, Bon Apetit lists several dry wines. The maxim that “If I wouldn't drink it, then I wouldn't cook with it” always holds true.

https://www.bonappetit.com/test-kitchen/cooking-tips/article/red-wine-for-cooking My penchant is to use an inexpensive table wine, like Rene Junot, or an inexpensive Southern Rhone. And don't be afraid to sip while you cook.

Made as directed using high quality basics (beef broth, butter, etc.). It was amazing. Once off the heat, I stirred in two tablespoons of good red wine vinegar. It was even better.

Zucchini lasagna

For sauce (or use a jar of sauce)

3 large garlic cloves

2 tablespoons unsalted butter

15-ounce can crushed tomatoes, fire roasted if possible

15-ounce can tomato sauce, fire roasted if possible

1 teaspoon dried or fresh basil

1 teaspoon dried tarragon or oregano

2 teaspoons kosher salt, divided

2 teaspoons cornstarch

2 pounds zucchini (3 large or 5 small medium)

2 ½ tablespoons chopped fresh thyme

2 teaspoons lemon zest (1/2 lemon)

1 ½ cups ricotta cheese

¾ cup shredded Parmesan cheese, divided

2 cups (7 ounces) shredded mozzarella cheese, divided

¼ teaspoon ground nutmeg

Fresh ground black pepper

Preheat: Preheat the oven to 450°F

Sauce: Mince the garlic. Add the butter to a medium saucepan over medium heat: once melted, add the garlic and saute until fragrant, about 1 minute. Turn down the heat and carefully add the crushed tomatoes, tomato sauce, basil, tarragon, ½ teaspoon kosher salt, and several grinds of black pepper. Remove ¼ cup of the sauce and stir it with the cornstarch, then add it back to the pan (this helps to thicken the sauce). Simmer while making the remainder of the recipe, at least 15 minutes. When ready to use, remove the pan from the heat. (YOU CAN ALSO USE CANNED SAUCE)

Roast the zucchini noodles: Slice the zucchini into noodles ¼ inch thick, using a knife or mandoline (if you have a mandoline, it’s the easiest way to get uniform pieces). You can discard the pieces that are just the peel. Place the zucchini strips on two parchment-lined baking sheets and drizzle them with olive oil, then use your hands to rub it so they are lightly coated on both sides. Sprinkle with 1 teaspoon kosher salt, divided across the 2 trays. Roast 10 to 12 minutes, until just tender. Remove the pans from the oven and set aside.

Meanwhile, prepare the cheese filling: Destem the thyme, then roughly chop the leaves. Add 2 tablespoons thyme to a medium bowl and reserve about ½ tablespoon for topping the lasagna. To the bowl, add the lemon zest, ricotta cheese, ½ cup Parmesan cheese, 1 cup shredded mozzarella cheese, nutmeg, ½ teaspoon kosher salt, and several grinds of black pepper. Stir to combine.

Turn down the oven: Turn down the heat to 375 degrees Fahrenheit.

Assemble the lasagna: In a 9” x 9” baking dish (or similar volume baking dish), spread a ½ cup tomato sauce on the bottom of the pan. Then top with 1 layer of the zucchini noodles, half of the cheese mixture (in dollops) and about ½ cup of the tomato sauce, using a spatula to spread the sauce evenly over the cheese. Repeat again, topping with 1 layer of noodles, the remaining cheese mixture, and ½ cup of the remaining tomato sauce. Finally, top with a final layer of noodles, then another ½ cup tomato sauce. Sprinkle the entire top with the remaining 1 cup mozzarella cheese, ¼ cup Parmesan cheese, and ½ tablespoon fresh thyme.

Bake the lasagna: Bake the lasagna for 40 minutes, uncovered. Let stand for at least 15 minutes before serving (this allows the lasagna to set; you can let it sit even longer if desired). Leftovers can be refrigerated for 2 to 3 days and reheated in a 375°F oven.

Recipe from: https://www.acouplecooks.com/perfect-zucchini-lasagna/#tasty-recipes-76318-jump-target

Strawberry Basil Farro Salad Bob's Red Mill Recipes

SERVINGS4-8 Servings

Ingredients

Farro

2 cups Organic Farro

4 cup Water

Dressing

2 Tbsp Minced Shallot about 3/4 oz

2 Tbsp Lemon Juice

1 Tbsp Balsamic Vinegar

1 Tbsp Honey

1 tsp Dijon Mustard

1/2 tsp Salt

1 tsp Poppy Seeds

1/2 cup Canola Oil or Light Olive Oil

Salad

1 lb Fresh Strawberries sliced

1/2 cup Toasted Sliced Almonds

2 oz Torn Basil

Preparation

Place farro and water in a pot and bring to a boil. Reduce heat to medium-low and simmer until tender, about 30 minutes. Drain and rinse with cool water, then drain thoroughly. Let cool completely and store chilled until ready to use.

To make the dressing, place all ingredients except the oil in a blender or food processor and process until smooth. Slowly stream in oil and let mix until smooth, creamy and emulsified. To make by hand, whisk together shallot, lemon juice, vinegar, honey, mustard and salt until smooth, then stir in poppy seeds. Whisking continuously, slowly add oil in small additions until smooth, creamy and emulsified. Store chilled until ready to use.

To assemble salad, toss farro, strawberries and almonds with dressing as desired. Add basil and gently toss to combine. Serve chilled or at room temperature.

Christmas Stollen, (from Bon Appetit, 12-20-2012)

Hot Bread Kitchen Head Baker Ben Hershberger's Stollen Makes 2 loaves

INGREDIENTS

FRUIT MIX (Make three days ahead of time)

1 cup raisins 1/2 cup dried cherries 1/4 cup candied lemon peel 1/4 cup candied orange peel 1 teaspoon vanilla extract 1/2 cup Meyers Rum 1/2 cup brandy Enough hot water to cover mixture

FILLING

5 tablespoons almond paste 1 generous tablespoon butter, at room temperature 1 tablespoon and 1 teaspoon sugar 2 tablespoon bread crumbs

SPICE MIX

1/2 teaspoon cinnamon 1/4 teaspoon ginger 1/8 teaspoon cardamom 1/16 teaspoon cloves 1/16 teaspoon nutmeg

DOUGH

1 cup blanched, unsalted almonds About a packet of instant yeast 1 1/3 cups King Arthur All-Purpose flour Scant teaspoon salt About 1 tablespoon milk powder 1/2 cup butter 2 tablespoons plus 1 teaspoon sugar 1 teaspoon spice mix (see above) 1/2 cup filling Fruit mix

ASSEMBLY

Melted butter, as needed Powdered sugar, as needed

PREPARATION

FRUIT MIX

Combine all ingredients and let soak at room temperature for at least three days.

FILLING

Combine all ingredients in the bowl of a stand mixer. While mixer is running on low, add 2 1/2 teaspoons water and mix until smooth. Divide mixture into two portions and refrigerate.

SPICE MIX

Combine all ingredients in a bowl.

DOUGH

Preheat oven to 325 degrees. Spread almonds in an even layer on a sheet pan and roast for 12 minutes. Turn oven up to 350 degrees and preheat.

Heat 1/4 cup plus 3 tablespoons water in a small saucepan to about 98 degrees. Pour into the bowl of a stand mixer, then sprinkle yeast over the top. Let set until all the yeast is dissolved and the water cools to about 80 degrees.

Add flour, salt, milk powder, soft butter, sugar, and spice mixture to the bowl and mix on medium speed until the dough is well developed (about 15 minutes). Gently fold in toasted almonds and drained fruit mix until evenly incorporated into the dough. Cover dough and let rest in a warm, draft-free area for one hour.

Divide dough into two even pieces, and roll each into 6-by-3-inch cylinders, then let rest for 20 minutes. Gently press both cylinders down with your hand until each is an even 1-inch thickness throughout. Holding a dowel the long way, neatly create a trough or canal down the center of each, about 3 1/2 inches wide. Place the chilled filling into one side of each the two troughs, covering the full length of the canals with the mixture. Fold the dough over the filling, cover, and let rest for 30 minutes.

Bake both loaves for about 25 minutes. Remove from the oven and brush liberally with melted butter, dust heavily with powdered sugar, and repeat to create a generous white coating. Let cool.

Wrap loaves separately in plastic. Stollen should set for at least one day before serving and can be eaten for up to three weeks.

Tips:

HOW Check your schedule. Your fruit needs to soak in its bath of rum, brandy, and hot water for a full three days before you bake the bread. After that, it should take about three hours from the time you start the dough to the moment your loaf is fully cooked. Here's how that breaks down, according to Hershberger: Preparing and mixing ingredients: 35 minutes. Dough fermentation: 1 hour, minimum. Shaping and resting the dough: 15 minutes. Shaping (again) the dough and letting it rise: 1 hour. Baking: about 25 minutes. Once it's out of the oven, the bread is topped with butter and sugar. Then, you should wait at least one day to let the stollen set before you dig in.

Hershberger's King Arthur flour of choice, the Sir Galahad, is a commercial product, but the company's all-purpose offering is a fine alternative. Otherwise, when making stollen at home, look for a European type 80 flour with a high ash content. If you cannot find this, you can also use regular bread flour, but, he advises, you'll have to adjust the moisture of your dough accordingly; bread flour doesn't absorb as much water.

What's most important, he says, is “not to get caught up in the recipe.” Stollen may be a complicated bread, but it allows for lots of creativity and improvisation. You can choose whichever kinds of dried fruit you prefer, and as much or as little as you like.

When you're shaping the stollen, put a bit of flour beneath the lump of dough. That should prevent it from splitting when, using a dowel, you form the canal for the almond paste.

Don't undermix your dough. It's the stollen crime most often committed. If your base isn't properly mixed and developed before you add the nuts and fruit, you'll be left with mush.

Shakshuka

Ingredients

1 tablespoon olive oil

1 medium onion sliced

1 medium red bell pepper sliced

2 cloves garlic minced

2 14 ounce cans diced tomatoes

1 teaspoon ground cumin

1 teaspoon paprika

1 teaspoon coriander

Salt and freshly ground black pepper

6 eggs

Fresh cilantro for garnish

Crusty bread for serving

Prep Time: 5 mins | Cook Time: 15 min | Total Time: 20 min

Preparation

Prepare the vegetables: Heat olive oil in a cast iron skillet over medium heat. Add the onions and peppers and cook for about 10 minutes until the onions become soft and translucent. Stir in garlic and cook for an additional minute until the garlic becomes fragrant.

Cook the tomato sauce: Pour the tomatoes, and add cumin, paprika and coriander. Season with salt and pepper. Bring to a boil, then reduce heat to low and simmer until the tomato sauce thickens like a stew, about 10-15 minutes.

I recommend using the traditional spices, which are cumin, paprika and cayenne pepper. But then you can add some coriander, caraway, red pepper flakes, chili powder and even sugar (which I don’t find necessary).

It’s important here to let the sauce simmer for a good 10 minutes. This will ensure that the sauce is not runny, but more like a stew. This will help hold the eggs in place too, so you don’t get scrambled eggs.

Create 6 small nests in the tomato stew. Gently crack the eggs into the skillet over the tomatoes in the nests formed. Season with salt and pepper. Cover the skillet, and cook until the egg whites have set, about 10 minutes. Garnish with fresh cilantro and serve with crusty bread or pita.

poached eggs in tomato sauce with crusty bread garnished with cilantro

Tips for Making This Shakshuka Recipe

For the best sauce consistency: It’s important to let the sauce simmer and allow it to thicken in order to hold the eggs in place. But be careful not to reduce the sauce too much. This made lead to it burning or sticking to the pan. It will all depend on the size of your pan and the thickness of the tomatoes to begin with.

For runny eggs: If you prefer the eggs more runny, you’ll want to reduce the sauce a couple extra minutes before cracking the eggs into the pan. Otherwise the sauce will run into the eggs, and we want to keep them separated for the most part.

For best presentation: If you want to make sure the dish doesn’t look like tomato scrambled eggs, make sure first that the sauce is thick enough, as I’ve mentioned earlier, and also make sure to create small indentations for dropping the cracked eggs. This allows the tomato sauce to nestle the cracked eggs in place, without having them spread out all over the pan.

How to Serve Shakshuka

For Breakfast: You really don’t need anything and can enjoy it as is. I love eating it with pita bread or a crusty bread, like sourdough or garlic bread.

For Lunch or Dinner: This pairs really well with a simple salad, like fattoush or a side like oven-baked fries.

Storage: Store any leftovers in an airtight container. They will last about 3-4 days in the fridge.

Serving: 2eggs | Calories: 207kcal | Carbohydrates: 7g | Protein: 12g | Fat: 14g | Saturated Fat: 3g | Cholesterol: 327mg | Sodium: 130mg | Potassium: 285mg | Fiber: 1g | Sugar: 3g | Vitamin A: 2045IU | Vitamin C: 54mg | Calcium: 68mg | Iron: 2.4mg